<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Preaching vvithout ordination or, A treatise proving the lawfulnesse of all persons, of what degree, ranke, or trade soever, being inabled with sufficient guifts and qualifications from God by his spirit, to preach and set forth the Gospel, though no minister nor any other officer in the church of God. By Edmond Chillinden.</title>
            <author>Chillenden, Edmund, fl. 1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E405_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201879</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862368</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862368</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114525</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79512)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 64:E405[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Preaching vvithout ordination or, A treatise proving the lawfulnesse of all persons, of what degree, ranke, or trade soever, being inabled with sufficient guifts and qualifications from God by his spirit, to preach and set forth the Gospel, though no minister nor any other officer in the church of God. By Edmond Chillinden.</title>
                  <author>Chillenden, Edmund, fl. 1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for George Whittington, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Blew Anchor in Cornehill neere the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 2d".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Preaching --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ordination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114525:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PREACHING VVITHOVT ORDJNATJON OR, A Treatiſe proving the lawfulneſſe of all Perſons, of what Degree, Ranke, or Trade ſoever, being inabled with ſufficient guilts and qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from God by his Spirit, to preach and ſet forth the Goſpel, though no Miniſter nor any other Officer in the Church of God.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Peter 4.10.</hi>
               </bibl> As every man hath received the guift, even ſo let him miniſter the ſame one to another, as good Stewards of the manifold graces of God.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Corinth. 14.31.</hi>
               </bibl> For you may all propheſie one by one.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalme 149.9.</hi>
               </bibl> This honour have all his Saints, prayſe ye the Lord.</q>
            <p>By Edmond Chillinden.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>George Whittington,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the ſigne of the Blew Anchor in <hi>Cornehill</hi> neere the Royall Exchange, 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114525:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114525:2"/>
            <head>To the Nationall Synod or Aſſembly.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have a few words to ſpeake to you, and they are to tell you, that I here preſent to your view this Treatiſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>viz.</hi> concerning Preaching without Ordination, and my deſire is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8.20. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21.</note> that you would reade and ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, trying all things therein, by the word of God, and if in the tryall it ſhall be found to corriſpond to truth, then quench not the ſpirit, nor diſpiſe the preaching therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for.</p>
            <p>But let me intreate you to take the Councel of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> which he ſpake to another Aſſembly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5.34.35.38.</note> ye men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> take heede to your ſelves what you intend to do, as touching theſe men, ſo I ſay to you, take heede to your ſelves what ye intend as touching the ſuppreſſing of preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel by the breathing of the Spirit of God in the hearts of his people (though not ordained by your humane Ordination.) Refrayne leaſt you be found fighters againſt God; for if this Councel and worke be of God (as by the Scriptures to mee it appeares to be of his right hands planting) then it ſhall ſtand and proſper.</p>
            <p>It is very ſtrange that you who would be counted the onely advancers and inlargers of the Kingdome of Chriſt ſhould riſe up in Armes againſt him, and with might and
<pb facs="tcp:114525:3"/> maine labour to ſuppreſſe the power that he hath ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine to conquer and bring under all Nations, and Kingdomes, to his ſubjection, the preaching and declaring the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the ſpirit by the word of truth, whereon God in Chriſt rides forth gloriouſly, conquering and to conquer, bringing in all thoughts and hearts to ſubject unto him.</p>
            <p>Did you but ſee the miſerable deſolations that the Divell hath made in moſt parts of this Kingdom upon poore ſoules and all for want of the powerfull preaching of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, ſo that I may ſay as the Prophet ſaith, my people periſh, and are deſtroyed for want of knowledge, ſo that thick darkneſſe covereth the whole face of this Kingdome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 11.12.</note> and the truth of God in the profeſſors and practiſers are the onely Butt, that wicked men ruled by the Prince of darkneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.6.</note> bend their bowes and make ready their arrowes upon the ſtring that they may privily ſhoote at the upright in heart.</p>
            <p>You cannot be ignorant, but this is the mayne deſigne of the Divell to hinder the propagation of the Goſpel by preaching, becauſe he knowes by the power thereof, Chriſts Kingdome is advanced and inlarged, and I am very confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the maine reaſon that hath impeded and obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the Parliaments juſt proceedings, and that the people in many parts of this Kingdome are ſo ill-affected, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not had the Lord Jeſus Chriſt held forth to them in the preaching of the Goſpel, for I have obſerved in my travills, ſince God called me into this Army, that in many of the Counties of <hi>England,</hi> there is not one Pariſh of tenn that hath one of your ordained men that is able to preach Chriſt, theſe things generally I have taken notice of, that where any of them are, they are either Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, uncleane perſons, dumb Idoles, or at the beſt cruel Malignants that have ever been oppoſite to the glory of God, the Parliaments juſt proceedings, ſo that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe
<pb facs="tcp:114525:3"/> in the Prophet is made true, like Prieſt, like people</p>
            <p>Therefore theſe things conſidered, I hope you will all of you to the utmoſt of your powers indeavour that Chriſt may be preached in every part and corner of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 11</note> that it may be full of the knowledge of the glory of the Lord, as the waters cover the Seas.</p>
            <p>What if ſome which are called Sectaries, and that of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my have preached Chriſt out of envy and contention, and not ſincerely; howſoever I know, and many thouſand ſoules beſides me can teſtifie that Chriſt hath been preached,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.15, 16, 17.</note> yea, and that effectually and powerfully to the prayſe and glory of God, and the comfort of many hearts, and I bid defiance to the Divell and all his blackmouthed Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to produce that ever thoſe that they call Sectaries, in preaching of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, did by that open a gap to prophaneſſe, or diſaffect the people from their loyall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Parliament, or their proceedings; but have gained them to yeeld ſubjection in bringing forth the peaceable fruits of godlineſſe, and righteouſneſſe towards God and men; therefore my thinks you and all people ſhould rejoyce, that Chriſt is preached, and God made knowne.</p>
            <p>Therefore refraine ye from that envious ſpirit, in cauſing the Mageſtrate to forbid us knowing that your ſelves are men of like paſſions with us, though you be the people and wiſdome ſhall die with you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 12.2.3. 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 14.36. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.8.</note> but there are thoſe that have underſtanding as well as you and are not inferiour to you, yea who knoweth not ſuch things as theſe, the word of God came not from you, neither came it to you onely, but as well to the reſt of the Saints, beſides you, ſeeing the wind bloweth where it liſteth, hould not back, neither hinder the blowings or breathings of it leaſt God come and fight againſt you with the Sword of his
<pb facs="tcp:114525:4"/> mouth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.9.</note> and ſlay you before him, becauſe you will not let him reigne over you nor his people; but I hope better things of you and things that accompany (the propogation, and ſetting forth the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by preaching as the way of) Salvation, ſo I reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours to ſerve Chriſt in the Goſpel;</hi> Edmond Chillenden, <hi>Lieutenant of Horſe in Colonel</hi> Wha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies <hi>Regiment.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Quarters at Kingſton upon Theames</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt the</hi> 20. 1647</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114525:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader, eſpecially my fellow Brethren and Saints, Commanders and Souldiers with mee in the Army, under his Excellency, Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX.</head>
            <p>THeſe are the dayes of <hi>Iacobs</hi> troubles wherein the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> begins to be multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, iniquitie geting the upper hand, doth with Iron ſinnewes, and the brow of braſſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face and beare down the word of exortation, ſo that now no man may ſtrive or reprove one another, the conſideration of which hath occaſioned mee to preſent you theſe following lines to conſider of, and if the Lord ſhall give yee underſtanding, in the knowledge of the truth herein contended for, feare not to Practiſe it, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the threats and menaces of men, though their words be ſtout, againſt the Lord, &amp; make the righteous offenders for a word, yet let thoſe that fear the Lord ſpeake oft to exort, teach, &amp; admoniſh one another in ſetting forth the Lord Jeſus Chriſt a Saviour for ſinners.</p>
            <p>Now all you that have taſted how good the Lord is and hath ſeene the goeings out of his Arme, before you, be not caſt downe nor diſcouraged, but with <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> reſolve not to flie, though <hi>Tobiaſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Sambalats</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Gods truth and people be never ſo greate, and
<pb facs="tcp:114525:5"/> mightie, and ſtirr themſelves never ſomuch; ſhall ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as we flie, ſhall we flinch, ſhall the voice of a damoſell now make us afraid and tremble, that have had the experience of a Gratious God preſerving of us, and making us to ſtand and oppoſe the fury of our enemies in the field, in the midſt of flaſhing flames, and ſhowers of fiery bullets, did he make us to have ſtout hearts to ſtare death in the face, and contemn the terrour thereof, ſhall we now diſtruſt him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe, farr be it from us for God is faithfull, and will never leave us nor forſake us, but ſhall and will ſtand by us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us out of all our troubles.</p>
            <p>I have only one word more to ſay, I know you with my ſelf had thoughts that though in the Biſhops dayes we ſnut our doers for feare of thoſe <hi>Iewes</hi> &amp; eat the bread of affliction, &amp; drank the waters of adverſity, yet now they being taken away &amp; the armies of the alians being put to flight, we had hope our eyes ſhould never have ſeen our teachers thruſt into cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners againe but ſhould have inioyed the ſweet fruit of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace and liberty in the free worſhiping of God, but you ſee God ordering of it otherwiſe; Therefore his hand being in it, we muſt conclud it is for his glory and for our good. (Let us with patience poſſeſſe our ſoules letting our moderation be known to all men, the Lord is at hand) &amp; give our cheekes to the nippers, and our backes to the ſmiters, and not to reſiſt authority, but patiently to beare and ſuffer what penalty ſhall be put upon us, for this is the will of God that by well doing we ſhould put to ſilence the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of fooliſh ſlanderous men that ſo report of us, &amp; that yee may ſoe doe it, ſhall be the prayer of him that is your brother and fellow ſouldier and companion in tribulation, and in the Kingdome, and patience of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Edmund Chillenden</hi> Liuetenant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114525:5"/>
            <head>PREACHING WITHOUT ORDINATION</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great controverſie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.26.27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. <hi>to the end Mat.</hi> 18.17 <hi>to</hi> 20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18.19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. <hi>to</hi> 12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>tota. Tit.</hi> 1.6. <hi>to</hi> 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, <hi>to</hi> 9. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.13.14.15.21. <hi>to end. Act.</hi> 6.1. <hi>to</hi> 7. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.25</note> or thing in this juncture of time is: Whether men (though by God furniſhed with gift<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and graces, and every way made able to diſpenſe the Goſpel;) may preach the ſame either private or publike, except they be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</p>
            <p>Therefore to make it appeare, that it is lawfull for men (ſo furniſhed and enabled by God,) to preach, publiſh, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Goſpel, though they be not by any Church or men ordained thereunto; I ſhall premiſe theſe things to conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Chriſt hath purchaſed unto himſelfe a Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That to this Church he hath given Lawes and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in his written word, by which they are to walke, and by none other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That in them he hath declared and ſet forth to his Church, what, and how many Offices, there are with Officers to be ſupplyed with their qualifications.</p>
            <p n="4">4. How the ſeverall Officers are to be inveſted, ordained, or put into their ſeverall Offices.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:114525:6"/>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Co.</hi> 12.13, 14. <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10.11 <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23.24.25. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.3.1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. <hi>tota. Titus</hi> 1.6. <hi>to</hi> 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.11. <hi>Act</hi> 2.3. &amp; 10.38. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.36. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 9.6.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3. &amp; 17.14.19.20. <hi>Act.</hi> 20, 28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.3.1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18 <hi>to</hi> 20.28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18 <hi>to end Pſal.</hi> 147.19.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Heb</hi> 3 2.6. <hi>Epheſ</hi> 1.22.23 <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.20. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19, 20, 21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18.10 <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2 <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 1 <hi>Gal</hi> 1 7 8 9. <hi>v.</hi> 1.2.3. <hi>chap. Epheſ.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Col.</hi> 23.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5 3.24. 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.1. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13, 19, 20 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Ro.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>compared vvith Mat.</hi> 18.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare that with Pſalme</hi> 149.8.9. <hi>and all them with</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5 16. 1 <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1, 2, 3. <hi>chap. Act.</hi> 1.21. <hi>to</hi> 26. <hi>and</hi> 6.2. <hi>to</hi> 6. <hi>and</hi> 14. <hi>to</hi> 23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. <hi>to</hi> 12. <hi>Tit.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. <hi>to</hi> 47. <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with Act.</hi> 6.2. <hi>to</hi> 6.14. <hi>to</hi> 23. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.16. <hi>to</hi> 27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 49. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. <hi>to</hi> 12. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5.7. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.15, 16, 26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.6.3.7.14.22.23. <hi>to end.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 4 3.</note>5. The manner how they are to manifeſt their guifts, par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and qualifications to declare their fitneſſe, that the Church may know and judge of them before they be ordained, that they may not be miſtaken in their choyce.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt being the annointed of his father, ſet on the Throwne of <hi>David,</hi> King of Saints, King of Kings, hath purchaſed to himſelfe by his blood, a Church which is a City, or body politick, whence it is called the City of God, of the great King, the body of Chriſt, his Temple, Orchard, Vineyard, nichoſed Garden, a royall Prieſthood, a holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a peculiar people, to offer up ſpirituall ſacrifices to God through Jeſus Chriſt the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Church or ſpirituall City he as their King and head, hath given lawes and ordinances in his written word, as rules by which ſhe is to be guided, and in them is layd downe to his people, all things needefull for life and godlineſſe to make the man of God perfect in the performance of the viſible worſhip of God, ſo that there is no neede for man or any ſort, Company or aſſembly of men, to deviſe or make lawes, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute Ordinances for his people, to obſerve in acting any thing concerning the worſhip and ſervice of God, or in the choyce or ordination of Officers in his houſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Church is ſet forth in the Scriptures to be particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar congregated, viſible Saints depending on none but Chriſt, in things concerning his ſpirituall Kingdome, it is not a houſe of lime and ſtone, nor a Congregation of viſible wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, no nationall, provinticall, dioſian Church, thoſe the Scriptures do not allow, nor in no wiſe declare, that God hath promiſed his bleſſing and preſence to dwell amongſt ſince the aſſention of Chriſt, and whence ſuch Churches came, and of whoſe deviſing they were, you may ſee in the Scripture cited. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.19 <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.1. <hi>to</hi> 11. <hi>to end Rev.</hi> 18 2.3.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thoſe have power given them, and it lyes in common to all and every of the Saints (members of the Churches of Chriſt) joyntly together to chooſe them Officers, as namely, (Paſtors, Teachers, Elders, Deacons) being the whole num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Officers I finde mentioned in the Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ures and to act in all other things given them in charge as Prayer-Preaching,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114525:6"/> receiving into fellowſhip judging of offenders and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the other Ordinances, this power doth not lye nor ever was given to the Officers, Miniſters, or Presbytery onely, that I can finde in the Scriptures, but to the ſeverall Congregations I finde that they had power to chuſe from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves men fitted and inabled by God, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the ſeverall Offices in his houſe and Sanctuary, to inveſt and ordaine them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If the Church have power, it muſt be ſuppoſed or gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that firſt there muſt be a Church, having this power be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there can be any Officers rightly and orderly ordained, except it can be maintained from the Scriptues, that there is Apoſtles ſtill, or men having an Apoſtolicall function which I conceive no where in Scripture is to be found; therefore if men may not preach before they be ordained, then how men ſhould be ordinarily converted to the faith, and order of the Goſpel I ſee not, becauſe faith comes by hearing, and hearing by the word preached, and if this be not granted, how and which way Churches can be gathered, and Officers ordained I cannot ſee except the Popes Ordination will ſerve which for my part I am loath to allow.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Againe for to chuſe one into Office preſuppoſes an apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and fitneſſe in the parties for the ſufficient diſcharge of that place unto which he is ſo called, choſen, or ordained, and it is granted of all ſides that the Officers of the Churches are ſo and ſo to be qualified as the Scripture ſets forth, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they be men of wiſdome, knowledge, grave, modeſt, of good report, both of them without, as well as with them within, full of the holy Ghoſt, apt to teach well, learned in Chriſt, no novice or youngling in the Schoole of Chriſt, to be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, alwayes ready to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the gaynſayers by ſound Doctrine, as he hath been taught the truth in Ieſus; theſe quallifications are required in the teaching Elders, or Biſhops, before they be ordained; therefore it is cleare, that the guift of utterance &amp; ſound know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by which a man is inabled to pray, preach, teach, declare, ſet forth Chriſt in the Goſpel not onely may, but muſt both be, and appeare to be in any men before they be choſen
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114525:7"/> into the office of the miniſtery,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. <hi>to</hi> 22. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 56.10.11. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.3.6 <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.23. <hi>Iob.</hi> 13.17. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4.20. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.54. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.15.16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13. <hi>compaire</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.3. <hi>to</hi> 6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 21.13.14. <hi>Chap. Rom.</hi> 22.6, 7 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>to</hi> 17. <hi>Col.</hi> 3, 16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. <hi>to</hi> 26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.3. <hi>to</hi> 6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.21.22.23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 44.33.40. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.14. <hi>to end. Act.</hi> 6.1. <hi>to</hi> 7</note> for he that is not a Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, or hath not the guift of preaching, before he be choſen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the miniſtery, is a dumb dogg and an idel Shephard; for the Office doth not give, (nor indeed cannot any whit increaſe) the <hi>guifts,</hi> or convey by the ſame any ſpirituall <hi>qualification</hi> or ability, onely gives a ſolemn charge and Commiſſion to uſe their guifts by vertue of their office they have received, This I ſuppoſe granted on all ſides.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Then it will eaſily be granted, that except men before they be choſen and ordained may be ſuffered and permitted to declare their guifts in Doctrine and Prayer (which are the maine things, &amp; that which is chiefly to be looked on, that the Paſtor or teacher is ſpecially to be qualified with) how ſhall the Church that is to chuſe them take knowledge of their ſufficiency, that they may both with faith and good conſcience, call them and ſubmit to them, And otherwiſe, for tryall of mens guifts (whereby they may be judged fit to be choſen into the Miniſtery, but onely by the way of preaching before Ordination by vertue of their guifts, I finde none, the the Scriptures are ſilent in it.</p>
            <p>But the other, that is propheſying or preaching, by <hi>vertue</hi> of the gifts and grace of God, before ordination or office; thus the Scriptures are very plentifull in manifeſting and declaring which God hath inſtituted for that end, that his Church may grow up thereby a compleate habitation, compleatly furniſhed with all her officers or ſervants, to ſupply all her ſeverall offices to the prayſe &amp; honour of Jeſus Chriſt her head, who hath inſtituted all things in order, he being the God of order hath left nothing in diſorder, but alwayes hath been carefull to provide for his houſe, not onely Officers to ſupply her in her ſeverall Offices; but alſo hath preſcribed a way and a rule for them in the chuſing them in their ſeverall Offices as is partly before ſpecified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But here ſome may ſay, that a man that is a good Scol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, having been at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> and ſtudied <hi>Divini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> may be permitted (as it is uſually practiſed in their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi>) to preach a Sermon two or three for approbation or tryall of his ſufficiency before he be ordained.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114525:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To this I anſwer, that it is not his learning,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. <hi>to end. Rom.</hi> 8.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19.20. <hi>and</hi> 2.1. <hi>to end.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.4.8.</note> nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny humane art; that will be ſufficient to inable him to be a Miniſter of the Goſpel, becauſe by that no man can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the minde and will of God in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe no man by his ſtudying or labour in humane things, can procure the gift of utterance whereby he may be inabled to ſet forth and declare Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. It is granted in the latter part of the objection, that it is lawfull and ſo practiſed by our adverſaries, to preach before ordination; therefore I do wonder why they ſhould condemne that in others, which they practice themſelves; for if a man may preach one Sermon, why not two, then why not twenty, and if one moneth, why not twelve moneths, and ſo I conceive, if it be lawfull thus to preach, as they themſelves grant, then the great controverſie about this poynt, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them and mee at an end.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But I further ſay, that it will not be ſufficient to preach a Sermon or two, whereby to judge of a mans fitneſſe, becauſe it is impoſſible that his gifts and qualification can be judged off, by any in ſo ſhort a ſpace, and ſo the Church to be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in their choyce, and inſtead of an able and painfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſet up a lying Idoll, dumb dogg, as it hath often fallen out in many of the Pariſhes of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Now I ſhall come to examine the ſeverall Scriptures that do hold forth the lawfulneſſe of all the Servants of God preaching before Ordination, I ſhall take them in order as they lye, and I ſhall indeavour to cleare them from thoſe falſe gloſſes which have been put on them, which have hindred the appearing of this truth, I ſhall alſo anſwer ſuch objections as ſeemingly may lye in the way.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Scripture to prove the thing in hand is written in <hi>Numbers:</hi> 11:26, to the 30, the words are theſe at the 26: verſe: but there remained, two of the men in the camp, the name of the one was <hi>Eldad,</hi> the name of the other was <hi>Medad,</hi> and the ſpirit reſted one them (and they were of them that were written, but went not out unto the Tabernacle) and they Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the Camp, and in the 29 verſe: <hi>Moſen</hi> ſaid would God that all the Lords people were Prophets the Lord will put his ſpirit on them (Reader take notice) <hi>Moſes</hi> here wiſhes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114525:8"/> that all the Lords people were Prophets, the Lord putting his ſpirit on them, I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe none will ſay that he wiſhed that all the Lords people were Prieſts or Levits (I meane ordained officiall men) but they were all Prophets.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.3.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6. <hi>to</hi> 9.</note> Teachers, or Preachers of Gods will, and minde, one to another for their good and edification, that which <hi>Moſes</hi> wiſheth here, is that all the Lords people were ſuch as <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> were, and they were no Officers, neither Prieſts nor Levites, and yet we finde they propheſied in the Campe, by reaſon of the Spirit of God, reſting on them, and not becauſe they were ordained Officers; for then I conceive <hi>Ioſuah</hi> would not have complayned of them, as may appeare in the 27.28. verſe but <hi>Moſes</hi> maketh it all one to be a Prophet, and the Lord putting his ſpirit on a man,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.14 <hi>to</hi> 29. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.12. <hi>to</hi> 24. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.15.16. <hi>Marke</hi> 4.21. <hi>Luke</hi> 8.16.17. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.7. <hi>to</hi> 17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.34.35. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.1. <hi>to</hi> 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19.20.27.28. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5. <hi>to</hi> 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11.16.17. <hi>and Mat.</hi> 11.25.26.</note> then why ſhould not men now, to whom God hath given of his ſpirit, with guifts of utterance and knowledge be a Prophet and Preacher, and that of the Lords owne making; for <hi>Moſes</hi> doth wiſh the uſe or exerciſe of Gods ſpirit and graces in men, as the having and poſſeſſing of them for the guifts of God are not given to be hidden under a Buſhell, or to be kept in a napkin, but to be made uſe of to the prayſe and glory of God, that is the giver of them, who hath given guifts unto men for the workes of the Miniſtery, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of his body, which is his Church and people, ſo then I thus argue, if any man now that is a Member of the Church of Chriſt, though not ordained unto whom God hath given ſufficient guifts, and qualifications by his Spirit, whereby he is made able to preach, he is not onely to poſſeſſe it, but to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it for the perfecting of the Saints labouring in the word and doctrine of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And ſeeing God is no reſpecter of perſons, but gives his guifts by his ſpirit to whom he pleaſeth, where by all men that partake of thoſe guifts are inabled to propheſie or preach, though not ordained what ſhould hinder them from being Prophets and Preachers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd that of the Lords own making, by the free guift of his ſpirit, ſeeing it bloweth where it lifteth, aſſoone upon a <hi>Cobl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, Tinker, Chimneyſweeper, Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> or any other Tradſeman, as to the greateſt learnedſt Doctors in the world.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:114525:8"/>
            <p>Then I here demand the reaſon, why he namely the <hi>Cobler, Tincker, &amp;c.</hi> may not be permitted, to manifeſt the gifts and graces of God in him, by Preaching and declaring the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel as the other: to wit the Learned man, I confeſſe my ſelf ignorant of any reaſon againſt it in the whole word of God, but greatly for it, and layes it on all men that have received the gift ſo to adminiſter:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10, 11.</note> ſo to uſe it as good Stewards of the manifold graces of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſome object and ſay, that this ſpirit here that thoſe, to wit <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> had, was not the ſpirit of propheſie, but of Government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, I ſhall not deny but they had the ſpirit of Government, but that they had not beſides it the ſpirit of propheſie, I leave by the wiſe to be judged; for looke into the text the 26 verſe of <hi>Numb.</hi> 11. and if we will not be will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blind, we cannot but ſee and know, they had alſo the ſpirit of propheſie.</p>
            <p>For ſaith the text, <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi> propeſied (or preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) in the Campe; Now if they had done nothing but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Government, without queſtion <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> would not haue deſired <hi>Moſes</hi> to forbid them, in regard that God had made known that he would take off the ſpirit that was on <hi>Moſes,</hi> and give it unto the ſeaventy, and this <hi>Joſhuah</hi> could not but know; For the Lord ſaith to <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the 16 <hi>ver. Gather unto me ſeaventy men of the Elders of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>whom thou knoweſt to be the Elders of people and Officers over them.</hi> Now from hence it is plaine that <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> knew they were Officers, (that is Magiſtrates) and if in point of Government it was that which they did, then I conceive <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> would not have ſaid <hi>Moſes</hi> forbid them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>The Lord ſaies I will come down and talke with thee, and I will take of the Spirit that is one thee, and will put it on them.</hi> Now it is cleere in the Scriptures, that <hi>Moſes</hi> had not onely a ſpirit of Government, but a ſpirit of Prophecy (or preaching of prayer and ſupplication);<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.15. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.15. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.37.</note> Therefore if God tooke of that ſpirit that was upon <hi>Moſes,</hi> and gave it to the ſeauenty whereof <hi>Eldad</hi> &amp; <hi>Medad</hi> were, then it cannot be reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned only to Government, but it muſt extend to all the reſt of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114525:9"/> operations and workes of it, as to prophecie or preach the great matters of Gods law to his people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſome may further object and ſay, theſe were Officers, and ſuch as <hi>Moſes</hi> knew to be ſo; therefore it will not follow from hence that all may preach though guifted, except they be Officers as theſe were.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I grant they were Officers in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Iſrael, to wit, Magiſtrates; but what is this to the thing in hand, to wit, Preaching without Ordination; for there is no mention that they were either Prieſts or Levites, or any Officers of the Church, neither did their Office bind them to propheſie; I leave it to be judged, whether it was any principall end in their Office, binding them to preach, neither can it be gathered from the Scriptures becauſe they were Officers therefore they preached; no, but becauſe God had powred on them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 32.18.19.20. <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2.28. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 44.3. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.17.</note> end filled them with the ſpirit as <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu</hi> like new bottles, and as wine that hath no vent; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they muſt ſpeake and open their lips that they might be refreſhed, and this was the cauſe of their propheſying or Preaching, becauſe of the powerfull worke and operation of the ſpirit of God in them, and not becauſe they were now Officers for that they were before this time, as is playne by the text, and Gods words to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the 16. verſe.</p>
            <p>The next Scripture I come now to handle, is the 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.7. verſe, and to the 8.9. verſe, where it is ſaid, that <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat</hi> ſent to his Princes to teach in the Cities of <hi>Judah,</hi> and they taught in <hi>Judah,</hi> and had the Booke of the Law of the Lord with them, and went about throughout all the Cities of <hi>Judah,</hi> and taught the people, whence it is evident, that the Princes of <hi>Judah</hi> that were no ordained Miniſters, preached the Law of the Lord to the people, with the Levites (a practiſe that thoſe who in our dayes call themſelves the Tribe of <hi>Levit</hi>) I could deſire that they would preſſ it upon the Princes of our times, thoſe who are furniſhed with the ſpirit of God to preach the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt to the people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amo:</hi> 8.11.12.</note> in our ſeverall Cities, that ſo there might not be that famine of the word, that is in the many parts of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, you ſee <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> did not queſtion their Ordination
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114525:9"/> neither did the Levites forbid any ſuch thing, ſo my thinks it would evidence a good heart in the Levites of our times to preſſe Princes and people, all that have guifts to preach Jeſus Chriſt to the people, that the earth might be full of the knowledge of the glory of the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Habak.</hi> 2.14.</note> as the waters cover the Sea, and not to be of the envious ſpirit with <hi>Joſuah,</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Magiſtrates to forbid them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 11.9.</note> becauſe they are not ordained by their humane Ordination; there was never any ſuch thing heard of, nor declared in the Scriptures, for it is evident in the writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.46.</note> that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their wiſe men as they are called in the Scriptures, might and ought to teach in their Synagogues without any regard or reſpect had to any Office or Ordination in the Church, we finde <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.35. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16.17. <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.29 <hi>Mat</hi> 23.34. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Ier.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5.</note> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6, 7, 8, 9.10, 11. verſes, confirming this to us how he preached to the Judges, and to the Levites, and alſo his divine and excellent prayer to God in the publike congregation &amp; of <hi>Ezekiah</hi> his Sermon in the very Temple of God, and ſo of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and others, who taught the people the Law of the Lord, a good patterne for our Princes now, and do we not reade free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in the Scriptures every where that the Scribes Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes and Lawyers, in any of which were no ordained Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, neither Prieſts nor Levites;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.54. <hi>to end. Marke</hi> 6.2. <hi>to</hi> 5. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.16, <hi>to</hi> 22. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.46. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.16. <hi>and</hi> 17.2.</note> yet taught publikely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Jewes, as appeares by the Scriptures, and if it were not ſo practiſed how comes it to paſſe that Jeſus the Sonne of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who was no ordained perſon, that is no Prieſt nor Levite in their Church, that they permitted him to diſpute in the Temple with the great Doctors, and to teach and preach frequently in the Synagogues as he did, and the like may be ſeene of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> that were no ordained Miniſters that the people of the Jewes tooke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, yet they preached frequently and publikely, and ſo it appeares, to be the conſtant practice hitherto ſet out in the Scriptures, to preach without Ordination.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſome may ſay, that Jeſus Chriſt was extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily indued with guiſts, and the like of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi> and taught by their extraordinary guifts, and were ſo permitted by the Jewes to preach.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114525:10"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>and</hi> 61.1.2.3.</note>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> He that ſo ſayeth that they were extraordinarily indued with guifts, ſpeakes the truth, though to little or no purpoſe to the matter in hand; for what was that (to wit, their extraordinary guifts) to the received order and practiſe in the Temple, &amp; Synagogues amongſt the Jewes, that did not believe in Chriſt nor acknowledge him, nor his Apoſtles in any ſuch way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Some may further ſay, that Ieſus was the Sonne of God ſent of God to preach, and <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and ſo might preach, becauſe they had an Office that did bind them to it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer againe that this is true, but beſides the matter, did the <hi>Iewes</hi> look on Chriſt as he was the Sonne of God? did they looke on <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> as Deſciples of Chriſt?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.34. <hi>to end. Marke</hi> 6.1. <hi>to</hi> 5. <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.46. <hi>to end. Mat.</hi> 13.34. <hi>to end. Marke</hi> 6.1. <hi>to</hi> 5. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.13. <hi>to</hi> 18. <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with</hi> 5.28 <hi>Acts</hi> 13.16.</note> I am ſure no man will dare to affirme it; becauſe the Scripture is againſt it. Wee find declared in the Scriptures, that the Iews look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on Chriſt with ſcorne and contempt in relation to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sonne of God, and ſay of him, <hi>Is not this Ieſus the Son of</hi> Mary <hi>the Carpenters Son, even of</hi> Ioſeph. <hi>Nay is not this Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the Carpenter,</hi> did they not hate and deſpiſe both him and his Apoſtles, and in the conſideration of his being a miniſter of the Church of God, or his Apoſtles any Officers, they did not beleeve at all; but onely according to the common cuſtome amongſt them, they permited Jeſus to preach and diſpute, and ſo was it that Ruler of the Synagogue ſent to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> that if they had a word of exortation to the people to ſay on; and not becauſe they were Officers or had any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination in the Rulers underſtanding, and ſo much ſhall ſuffice for this particular. I now come to the next Scripture,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> the 18.24 to the end, where it is thus ſaid, <hi>A certain Iew named</hi> Appolloes <hi>borne at</hi> Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ndria, <hi>an eloquent man and mighty in the Scriptures, came to</hi> Epheſus; <hi>this man was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the way of the Lord, and being fervent in the Spirit he ſpake, and taught dilligently the things of the Lord, knowing onely the baptiſme of</hi> Iohn, <hi>and he began to ſpeak boldly in the Synagogue; whom when</hi> Aquila <hi>and</hi> Priſcilla <hi>had heard, they took him unto them and expounded unto him the way of God were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly.</hi> And in the 28 <hi>ver.</hi> it is thus ſaid, <hi>For he mightily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced the Iews &amp; that publickly, ſhewing by the Scriptures that</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114525:10"/> Jeſus was the Chriſt. Reader, thou ſeeſt what is recorded in the Scriptures of this man Appollos how he preached Jeſus Chriſt diligently and that publickly in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and yet thou ſeeſt there is no office nor Ordination which is at this time once hinted as that he had, and yet he preached the Goſpel by reaſon of his fervency in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: ſo that was the cauſe of his ſo boldly ſpeaking and teaching in the Synagogue: and that he had no Office nor Ordination at this time, I ſhall give thee theſe reaſons 1. Becauſe the Scripture is altogether ſilent in it and doth not once hint any ſuch thing. 2. Becauſe we onely finde this mentioned of him in the Scripture, that he was inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the way of the Lord being fervent in the Spirit, ſpake and taught boldly mightily convincing the Jews,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 18.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and that publikely ſhewing by the Scriptures that Jeſus was the Chriſt. 3. He knew the Baptiſme of John he was ſo far taught in the way of the Lord to imbrace Chriſt as that he went beyond the Jewes and ſo could be no officer in the Church of the Jewes.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He could not be any officer in the Chriſtian Church, becauſe he knew onely the Baptiſm of John he was not yet come far enough in the knowledge of the Goſpel for that: Theſe reaſons I conceive are ſufficient to evidence to all men that are not guided by a partiall Spirit that Apollos here preached not by vertue of any office or ordination but by the vertue and power of the Spirit of Gods operation in him.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay this man was extraordinarily guifted by God, and ſo by his extraordinary gift preached. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer that ſome things eſpecially above other man is recorded of him, as that namely he was a very eloquent man, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 18.24.</note> and that he was mighty in the Scriptures, and that he boldly taught, and that by his teaching, he mightily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced the Jewes, but that this did prove that he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily indued with guifts from God I cannot ſee, but do beleeve the contrary, and for that I ſhall offer the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe reaſons, firſt, becauſe if God had extraordinarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired him, he could not have been ignorant of the revealed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114525:11"/> will, way, and Councell of God declared in the Goſpel, and onely to have knowne the Baptiſme of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.26.27.</note> for none that God did ſo inſpire, but did know the whole Councel of God revealed, as witneſſe <hi>Paul</hi> and all the oiher Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.28, <hi>and</hi> 16.13, <hi>to</hi> 16.</note>2. Becauſe if he had been ſo inſpired, then he would had no neede of Aquillaes and Priſcillaes teaching or more perfect learning him the way of God, for then he might better have taught them, but we finde that when they had heard him, they tooke him unto them, and expounded or ſhewed him the way of God more perfectly, and therefore for theſe reaſons is it that I beleeve he was not extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y guifted of God, and ſo much may ſerve to evidence the truth from thoſe falſe gloſſes and miſinterpretations, that ſome have indeavoured to put upon this Scripture to hinder the Saints from following the rule and example of Chriſt and his faithfull Servants ſet forth to us in the Scriptures, in preaching and declaring the Goſpel without Office or Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to Acts 8, 1, 4. compared with Acts 11.19, 20, 24. Where it is thus written, And at that time there was a great perſecution againſt the Church that was at Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and they were all ſcattered abroad throughout the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of Judea and Samaria except the Apoſtles; and in the 4. ver, it is ſaid thus, therefore they that were ſcattered abroad went every where preaching the word, and in Acts 11.19, 20, ver. Thus now they that were ſcattered abroad upon the perſecution that roſe about <hi>Stephen</hi> travailed as far as Phenice and Cyprus and Antioch preaching the word to none but the Jewes onely &amp; ſome of them were men of Cyprus and Cyreene, which when they were come to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och ſpake unto the Grecian preaching the Lord Jeſus and the hand of the Lord was with them and a great number believed and turned to the Lord; here (Reader) conſider ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly what God by his Spirit hath recorded in theſe places of Scripture for our learning, if it be well minded God doth as it were point out to us his foreſeeing the errour, and evill that men in this point would run into and therefore ſaith that all the Church except the Apoſtles were ſcattered, ſo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114525:11"/> that I conceive that God doth point out here that the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſtaid behinde and thoſe that were ſcattered and went preaching the Goſpel were no ordained men to that end, And I conceive it cannot be thought, nor gathered from what is in the Scripture related that theſe that were ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered this whole Church were miniſters, ordained men, namely Paſtours, teachers or Elders, it ſeems ſomewhat ſtrange to me that the whole body of a Church ſhould be ordained Miniſters for that were to make the body mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous, and diſorderly, becauſe, as the Apoſtle ſaith 1. Corinth. 12, 17, ver. If the whole body were an eye where were the hearing? if the whole were hearing where were the ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? but now hath God ſet the members every one of of them in the body as it hath pleaſed him ſo that it is cleare that if God be the God of Order and doth all things orderly it cannot be thought that the whole body of this Church being at Jeruſalem with the Apoſtles were all ordained Miniſters,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 8.1.3.</note> they conſiſting at leaſt of three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand perſons, ſuch a thing was never heard of, nor yet never any Scripture produced holding forth or hinting any ſuch thing, for in theſe Scriptures here is onely thus much ſaid, the whole Church at Jeruſalem except the Apoſtles were ſcattered, and they being ſcattered went preaching every where Jeſus Chriſt and this is all that is in the Scripture mentioned of them, and no office nor ordination at this time minded.</p>
            <p>But though they had no office all of them yet ſome of them had, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> and the reſt were extraordinarily by God inſpired and guifted by his Spirit.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe there is mention of Philip who was an ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed officer as you may ſee in Acts the 6. and the 5. ver. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> But what office is it that he had, not an office binding him to preach, his being ordained into that office was to no ſuch and as you may ſee in Acts 6.1, 2. There it is declared that Philipe office was to ſerve tables, to look to the daily adminiſtration for the poor, to wit a Deacon, and not to preach the Goſpel for that was beſides his office, and no and of being ordained: this I leave by the wiſe to be judged</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:114525:12"/>
            <p>That they were extraordinarily inſpired to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeems un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, and that for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt. Becauſe there is not the leaſt tittle in the text than giveth any hint that way. Secondly, Becauſe the onely titles given them are all the Church that was at Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem except the Apoſtles were ſcattered and they were ſome of them men of Cyprus and Cyrene, and nothing minded in the leaſt of extraordinary gift or endowment. Thirdly, Onely their preaching here and there is noted and ſpoken of, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and that by reaſon of their perſecution they became ſo ſcattered and not by reaſon of any extraordinary gift be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 8.3, <hi>and</hi> 11, 19, 20.</note> 4. Becauſe that if ſo be they had had any Apoſtolicall function or ordination or extraordinary gift of the Spirit then in my underſtanding there had not been any need of ſo ſuddain (nay not at all) of a ſending of Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas from Jeruſalem to Antioch,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 11.22 23.29.</note> though he were a good man and full of the Holy Ghoſt to ſettle and confirm the diſciples which they by their preaching had begot to the faith.</p>
            <p>For I conceive that any extraordinary gifted man or men amongſt them was well able to have done that work as Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20, <hi>and</hi> 3.5. 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 19 20.21.</note> and let any ſhew out of the Scriptures that where the Apoſtles did preach and beget to the faith that there went out or was ſent any to confirm it better after they had begun is, but ſuch was the ſending here of Barnabas, therefore for theſe and the like reaſons I conclude that theſe men th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Church that was thus ſcattered and went preaching the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel begetting men to the faith and obedience of the Goſpell, were not officers neither ordinary nor extraordinary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nor any ordination to any ſuch thing, neither any extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y gift or endowment: but ordinary ſuch as God promiſed to pour upon all fleſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.28, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which theſe having received ſome tal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lents of the Spirit of God, ſuch was the power of the grace of Love ſhed abroad in their hearts that they could not but ſpeak and declare thoſe they had ſeen and heard making uſe of that ſaying, when thou art converted thy ſelf ſtrengthen thy brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But ſome may further object and ſay, they did not preach, they did but diſcourſively declare Chriſt in the Goſpel which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114525:12"/> no man is againſt.</p>
            <p>I underſtand by preaching of the Goſpel, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> is no more then to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to publiſh to bring to make known, &amp; declare glad tidings as by the Scripture cited may appear:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>and</hi> 8.39. <hi>Mark</hi> 5.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.32. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1 1. <hi>to</hi> 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13.</note> it is not to go up into a pulpet to be apparelled in black, to make a long and tedious oration of far fetcht tales, out of the old and ancient fathers both popiſh and heathen, but to declare Gods will and minde to his ſervants that he hath revealed to them by his Spirit agreeable to the word, and this I finde to be the ſubſtance of preaching the Goſpel, was it not the ſame that the Angels did in the ſecond of Luke. And the blinde man in Luke the 8. And the woman of Samaria John the 4. Two of theſe preached ſo effectually that they begat faith in the hearers, and how faith can be wrought in perſons in an ordinary way without preaching you may conſider the Scriptures cited.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14. <hi>to</hi> 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Again it is more then can be gathered from the text that they did but diſcourſe, for the text ſaith they Preached,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 4.2, <hi>and</hi> 5, 42 <hi>and</hi> 8.25, <hi>and</hi> 9.20, 27 <hi>and</hi> 10, 36 37, <hi>and</hi> 17, 1, 2.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 18.4.20, 7, <hi>act</hi> 8, 30, <hi>compa.</hi> 35.37.</note> and if we look into other places of Scripture that ſpeaks of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we ſhall finde the ſame expreſſions that is here uſed, and therefore ſtrong reaſon there is to beleeve that this preaching was ſuch as the Apoſtles uſed, as may be ſeen in the Scriptures cited.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That they did diſcourſively preach Chriſt, I will not, nor dare not deny, but that they did that onely, is more then can in my underſtanding be concluded from the Scriptures. For I finde that Philip when he joyned to the Eunuches Charriot did uſe intercourſe of ſpeech ver. the 30. and 31. but ver. the 35. we finde Philip to have begun at that place, of Scripture and preached Chriſt to the Eunuch ſo long without any intercourſe of ſpeech, till he had by the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full work of Gods Spirit wrought faith in the Eunuch: to beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt, and to ſubmit to him in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Baptiſme: as may appear by ver. 36. Therefore I think it is clear that he preached in that way of preaching that is ſo much contended for.</p>
            <p>The next Scripture that offers it ſelf to be looked on in this particular of preaching without ordination is in the 1. Peter the 4.10, 11, ver. where it is thus written as every
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114525:13"/> man hath received the guift even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another, as good ſtewards of the manifold graces of God: if any man ſpeak let him ſpeak as the Oracles of God, if any man miniſter let him doe it as of the ability that Godgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, that God in all things may be glorified through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be praiſe and dominion for ever and ever Amen. For the underſtanding of the underſtanding of the intent of the Holy Ghoſt, here we are to conſider the words as they lye, and the Apoſtle ſaith as every man hath received the gift all perſons in generall of the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Church not to the Officres or Miniſters onely, but to all without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to office or ordination that have received the gift, they all as they have received ſo they ought and they are bound to Miniſter (that is preach) and declare it one to another that they may be good, faithfull in diſcharging of the truſt and ſtewardſhip committed to them,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2</note> as every man hath received the gift, (that is) as every one hath received this, and another that, and every one hath received he ought to offer the ſame as a free and willing offering towards the building up of the ſpirituall houſe and Church of God, as the Iſraelites of old did every one that was willing whoſe Spirit within ſtirred him up,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod</hi> 35.5. <hi>comp. Re.</hi> 20. <hi>to</hi> 29.</note> did come and bring accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as they had received towards the building of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle: and it is to be taken notice of that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e here towards the building of the Tabernacle there was one admitted only the Prieſt and the Levite, they that were conſecrated and in holy Ordination, but every one whoſe hand was willing brought as he had received,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.7. <hi>to</hi> 15. <hi>Collo.</hi> 2.19.</note> and God excepted of it as a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice well pleaſing in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſight, ſo now towards the building of the Spirituall houſe of God, God hath given gifts unto men for the work of the ſame and doth require our freeneſſe and willingneſſe to offer the ſame as he hath commanded for the perfecting of the ſain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that they may increaſe with the increaſing of God, and thus much is clearly held forth in theſe words, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> as every man hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he gift ſo let him him adminiſter the ſame.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay the Apoſtle hath not to do here with preaching, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> but with hoſpitality. To which I ſay that the Apoſtle hath from the 8. and 9 verſes to the 12. nothing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114525:13"/> elſe in hand but to exhort this Church, and by them all the ſervants of God to the exerciſe of the grace of love, which is ſhed abroad in their hearts, and doth not love ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? and is it not the Apoſtles minde and intent here to inſtruct the ſervants of God how they ſhould improve his grace of love in all manner of wayes, that they migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bring glory to him and good to his Church and people, is not this his main aime and intent? doth not he end and conclude with this ſaying? that God in all things may be glorified, then as God is honoured and glorified when his people are full of Charity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 61.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17</note> and do extend the bowels of mercy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to them that ſtand it need: to feed the hungry, to clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he he the naked, to harbour the ſtranger, thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I hope the great adverſaries againſt preaching without Ordination will not denie, but it is the duty of all perſons that to doe, or elſe I am afraid they would not have ſo many good gifts of their good Maſters and D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e as they have had ſo is it not the duty lying upon all as they have received the gift, ſhould by the grace of love extend and hold forth the bowels of mercy and compaſſion and riches that is in Jeſus Chriſt, to clothe the naked and diſtreſſed ſinner with the robe of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, to refreſh their thirſting ſouls with ſtreames that may glad the City of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.25. <hi>and</hi> 46.4.</note> fill their hungry ſouls with Angels food even the hidden Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; I conceive here is a moſt reall manifeſtation of the grace of love, when we extend it liberally with both hands and not ſparingly, therefore I conceive it is very clear, that the Apoſtles words are not to be reſtrained onely to outward hoſpitality and charity for the body, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey that ſhall ſo do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, cannot but doe violence to the text, and wrong the meaning of the Spirit (in my apprehenſion.)</p>
            <p n="2">2. Again conſider the Apoſtles exhortation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of a manifold grace, not of one us of hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ver. 9. bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to all and generall the gifts and graces of God for the which end the Apoſtle in the 11 and 12. verſes brings two things, Firſt the gift of preaching in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak as the Oracle of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly if any man miniſter let him doe it as of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114525:14"/> ability that God gives, ſo that by this it is cleare, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hath ſome thing elſe in hand beſides hoſpitality, to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> preaching and declaring the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, and that by vertue as they have received the gifts of the Spirit, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how any can make ſuch a conſtruction as that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ſcope of the Apoſtle and meaning of the Holy Ghoſt is to be reſtrained onely to ver. 9. I leave by the wiſe to be judged, how it hath the leaſt ſutableneſſe to the analogy of faith, but as the Apoſtle ſaith as every man hath received the gift, this I conceive is his intent, that even ſuch men mutually together in the bond of love communicate this their gifts as good and faithfull ſtewards of the manifold grace of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Collo.</hi> 3.14.</note> and a manifold grace is not one grace, but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitality is but one grace, but to the exerciſe of a manifold grace, is it here that the Apoſtle doth exhort the people of God to the adminiſtring of them, not onely to be barbarous, for that were the miniſtring of but one grace, and one is not divers or manifold, and ſo I come to the next Scripture, which is the 1. of <hi>Corinth,</hi> the 12. verſe 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>But the manifeſtation of the ſpirit is given to every man to profit withall.</p>
            <p>At the 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 14. verſe. 1. follow after Charity, and deſire ſpirituall guifts, but rather that yee may prophecie compare with the verſes 3. the 23, 24, 25, 26, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 39. the Apoſtle in this Epiſtle, and in the places cited, treates very largely of the exerciſe of the guifts and graces of God in propheſying or preaching the Goſpel by all men that are inabled thereunto with ſufficient guifts from God, and this the Apoſtle preſſes on them by the exerciſe of the grace of love, as is ployn if we look into the 12.13. and 14. Chapter before cited and in the beginning of the fourteenth Chapter he ſaith follow after Charity and deſire ſpirituall guifts, but rather that ye may propheſie, now we are to take notice, who it is that the Apoſtle exhorts to the exerciſes of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of love, and that is as may be ſeene in the comparing what the Apoſtle, ſaith in the firſt verſe in theſe words, but rather that ye may propheſie the (ye) that he meanes here in the 23. verſe, appeares to be the whole Church, excluding none that have guifts, ſo that I hope none can have any ground to think
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114525:14"/> that this his exhrtation was minded or intended onely to the Miniſters, Officers, or ordained men in the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth:</hi> he writes and exhorts the whole Church to covet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the beſt guifts, but rather that they might propheſie, and this he perſwades them to, by an argument drawne from the excellent benefit that came to them by the having and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing of it, as may be ſeene in the 3. verſe, he that preaches ſpeaketh to men for their edification, exhortation, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, it is the excellent way that God hath ordained to beget men to the faith, to diſcover the ſecrets of their hearts, to convince men of the truth of God, and the way of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as may be ſeene in verſe the 23. to the 26. and this the Apoſtle preſſes upon the whole Church, and that this whole Church ſhould be all of them ordained men, to men it ſeemes ſomwhat ſtrange, I think it be ſo miraculous a thing, as it is beyond all imagination, never read of in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, nor heard of in any age of the world; ſo that then it wil appeare, &amp; muſt be granted that the Apoſtles exhortation extends generally to all men, Members of the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> without reſpect had to Officer or Ordination, to covet earneſtly to preach, and declare the Goſpel as he ſaith in verſe 31. ye may all prophecie, yea all the whole Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> that have guifts, one by one, that all may learne, and all may be comforted, wherein is to be noted that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeakes of all preaching, as largely and univerſally as all learning, from whence I ſtill affirme and thus argue, that all thoſe now that are the Servants of God,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. <hi>to</hi> 26. <hi>Jude</hi> 20. <hi>Rom</hi> 12.6. <hi>to</hi> 9. <hi>and</hi> 15. <hi>and</hi> 14. <hi>Object.</hi>
               </note> that have received guifts from him, whereby they are inabled to preach and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpel, though no Officer, neither having any Ordination may, ought, nay they are bound, and woe be to them if they preach not the Goſpel, a neceſſity is layd upon them to do it, and to exhort others to the practice of it, as our Appoſtle here doth, ſeeing we are to follow them as they followed Chriſt, and we finde that in all their Epiſtles, they ſtill multiply exhortations to the Churches in this nature, as may be ſeene in the Scriptures cited.</p>
            <p>But ſome may object and ſay, that though they were not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114525:15"/> Officers, nor had any Ordination, yet they were extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily guifted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I make this anſwer, that this to think much more to affirme is very abſurd, and tha for theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, becauſe it was never heard of, nor in all the written word of God hinted at, eſpecially concerning this Church of the <hi>Corinths,</hi> that the whole body of them were extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily guifted, 2. becauſe the Apoſtle doth reſtrayne woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from preaching, or others ſpeaking in the Church, from whence it is playne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.36. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15 20. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 4.24.</note> that this propheſying is ordinary, and lies in common to all the Servants of Jeſus Chriſt, for woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that were extraordinarily guifted I affirme, and the Scripture cited with me might preach, and did without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, ſo that from hence I thus argue, that the Apoſtle for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding and prohibiting woemen from preaching, gives li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to all men guifted for to preach, and againe I argue from this ground, that they were not Officers ordained, nor extraordinarily guifted, becauſe the Apoſtle oppoſeth women to men, Sex to Sex, and not woemen Officers or extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary guifted men; for then I conceive the Apoſtle would nor have aid, let your woemen keep ſilence in the Churches, for it is not permitted for them to ſpeake; but the Apoſtle would have aid, let your woemen keep ſilence in the Churches becauſe they are no Officers, nor have any Ordination, not any extraordinary guift, therefore they are to be ſilent in the Churches; but he ſaith it is not permitted for them to ſpeake, not out of any ſuch conſideration, as before minded, but becauſe of the Command of God, they are to be under obedience, and to learne in ſilence, for it is a ſhame for woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to ſpeake in the Church. 3. becauſe the Apoſtle exhorts that the Church ſhould judge of the Doctrine that theſe Prophets or Preachers ſhould teach, as appeares by verſe 29. let the Prophets ſpeake two or three, and let the reſt judge for the ſpirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets, now if they were extraordinary Prophets, and infallibly guided, they could not err; and ſo the Apoſtle might have ſpared his labour of preſſing them to judging of their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114525:15"/> Doctrine delivered;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20.35. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7.8</note> for ſuch Prophets or Preachers as were extraordinarily guifted I affirme could not err, and ſo were not ſubject to any ſuch Judgement as the Apoſtle calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for at the hands of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and for any to ſay that Prophets extraordinary could or might err, is to weaken and ſhake greatly the ground and piller of our faith, and if they might err, then the Apoſtles, and if in Doctrine taught why not in writing, and if this were true, we were of all men moſt miſerable, but we know we have a more ſure word of prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecie, whereunto we do well to take heede, and diligently to marke and ſtudy, and upon this ſure word we know is our faith, built even of the Prophets and Apoſtles,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.</note> that we are guided by the unering ſpirit of God, &amp; need not their Doctrine, ſhould be called in queſtion, or ſo judged by any of the Sonnes of men; therefore theſe Prophets here ſpoken of were not extraordinary, but ordinary, by reaſon the Apoſtle commands the reſt of the Church to judge, and try their Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Agayne the Apoſtle ſaith in the 37 and 38 verſes, that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man think himſelfe a Prophet or ſpirituall, let him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the things that I write are the Commandements of God; but if any man be ignorant, let him he ignorant ſtill, by all which it appeares plainly, that they were but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Prophets or Preachers, and had no other then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry guifts and indowments, for could they be thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s infallibly guided by the ſpirit, and yet muſt <hi>Paul</hi> call on them to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the things he writ, were the Commandements of the Lord Jeſus, in my underſtanding, he might have ſaved this labour, for he could not but know that ſuch that had the ſame meaſure and manner of the infallible ſpirit with him could not be ignorant of the Doctrine and Commands of Chriſt; therefore it is moſt apparant and playne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they were but ordinary Preachers, and preached by an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary guift, ſuch as is common by the promiſe of God, to be powred forth upon all fleſh, and hence is it that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the cloſe of all, exhorts them to the uſe and ſtudy of this preaching, and declaring of Jeſus Chriſt, as appeares in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114525:16"/> the 39. verſe in theſe words, wherefore brethren, covet to propheſie or preach; where is to be noted, he puts them on to the uſe and ſtudy of meanes, even the word and Goſpell of God which is able to make the man of God perfect to all good workes,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.17.</note> thereby furniſhed, ſo that in my underſtanding it cleerely appeares they were not extraordinary Preachers, but ordinary, for extraordinary Prophets or Preachers were at no time exhorted to any ſuch thing, that ever I read of, to the uſe and ſtudy of meanes immediately to be fitted or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1. <hi>to</hi> 5.</note> but immediately without any meanes freely given to them of God, without any ſtudy or labour, as may be ſeene plentifully in the Scriptures cited; ſo that from all that which hath been ſaid, it is moſt apparant and cleare, and that from the further exhortation which the Apoſtles uſes to the Churches and Saints of God, it is lawfull, yea, neceſſary for them to preach, to declare to make knowne, and ſet forth, yea and that publikely, the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, for our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaith, that which I have told you in your eares, do you preach upon the houſe tops, and the Apoſtle in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. at the 6. ſaith having then guifts differing according to the grace that is given unto us (not Ordination) whether pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie let us propheſie according to the proportion (of what) (not Ordination but of Faith) and the Apoſtle exhorts the <hi>Colloſians</hi> the 3. and 16. to have the word of Chriſt dwell in them richly, in all wiſdome, whereby they ſhould be inabled with grace in their hearts (not Ordination) to teach and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh one another, and build them up in their moſt holy faith, the ſame Apoſtle in <hi>Hebrews</hi> the 10.23. to the 25. verſe provokes that Church to hold faſt the profeſſion of Faith, without wavering, to conſider one another, to provoke one another to love, and to good workes, to exhort one another, and blames them in the 5. Chapter and the 12. verſe, for not being frequent in the exerciſe of the guifts of the ſpirit in preaching the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, by which they might for the time have been teachers of others, and for the neglect they had neede to be taught themſelves againe the firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion, there be ſome Scriptures more which is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114525:16"/> caſt in the way as oppoſing this truth in Romanes the 10 and 15. how ſhall they preach except they be ſent? and ſo they argue that ordination is the ſending here intended, but that there is any ſuch thing here minded peruſe the Scripture; I underſtand the ſending here is the being furniſhed with gifts from God inabling them to make known God through the preaching the Goſpel that thoſe that heare it may beleive, and ſo much my thinks the Apoſtle argues from the 13 to ver. the 18. and minds nothing of any office or ordination but only the gifts and maniſtations of the Spirit bring the Goſpel of peace and glad tidings of good things, another Scripture which is alledged the 1 of Corin. the 7. Chap. ver. 20. let every man abide in the ſame calling wherein he was called whence it is alledged that a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Gods providence called to this or that trade he ought therein to abide, and ſo from thence that preaching of the Goſpel is a trade for ſome men to abide in, now to clear and ſet forth the Apoſtles meaning here conſider the ſcope of the Apoſtle which he hath here in hand, and that is this, that in whatſoever perticular calling or trade and in what particular relation and ingagements men were, in whether bond or free Circumciſion or uncircumciſion, Jew or Gentile, whether maſter or ſervant, whether married if by the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt they were called to beleive, they in the ſame relations condition, bond or tie were therein notwithſtanding their now being beleivers to abide with God, for the Apoſtle ſaith in the 21 ver. and 22. Art thou called being a ſervant care not for it: now I hope none will ſay that Calling i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to the Miniſtery, the Apoſtle exhorts here he ſhould not care for it and none will ſay that men being called to the office of the miniſtery ought not to take care, but diligently to wait upon the Miniſtery, it is evident the Apoſtles meaning, by calling here is the bringing of men by the power of the Goſpel out of a ſtate of unbelief and infidelity to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo being husbands or wives, maſters or ſervants, they were therein to abide with God and to know that their now being believers did not break their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114525:17"/> civill ties or relations and this is that which the Apoſtle here intends from verſe the 12. to verſe the 25. and doth not at all minde any calling to any office or ordination to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, neither doth make it here or in any other place of Scripture a trade to preach the Goſpel: but generally through the whole Scripture layes it down as the generall calling which belongs to all the Saints by vertue of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing intereſted into Chriſt by the power of the Spirit in the preaching of the Goſpel; and ſo much for the preſent I offer by the wiſe to be conſidered and tryed by the Scriptures in the Spirit of love and meekneſſe. Now for concluſion I ſhall onely adde thus much from all that which hath been ſaid, that it doth appear to me very cleare that God hath laid it upon all men believers in Jeſus Chriſt ſo as they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved gifts whereby they are inabled with knowledge and utterrance to ſet forth, teach and declare Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpel that they ought to doe it as good and faithfull ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of the gifts and graces of God,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Peter</hi> 4.10.11. 1 <hi>Corin.</hi> 4.1.</note> God requires it of them and they may not neglect it, nor no man may forbid them without manifeſt breach of Gods holy will and commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5.29. <hi>and</hi> 4.19.</note> and therefore let us conſider whether to obey God that ſaith unto us, what I have ſpoken to you in ſecret that preach, declare and make knowne on the houſe top, and as you have received gifts for the work of the miniſtery, ſo let us labour in the word &amp; doctrine to build up and perfect the Saints in our moſt holy faith and not feare man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 20.</note> or the ſon of man who is lighter then vanity, but let us feare God and obey his Commandement for that is good and acceptable in his fight: without which doing none of the Saints can diſcharge faithfully that truſt committed and given to them, for we muſt imploy his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents labouring in his vineyard which is his Church that he may have the praiſe and glory of all his works and graces in them, and therein we ſhall greatly manifeſt our faithfulneſſe to God, our juſtneſſe in diſcharge of the truſt committed to us, and in that conſideration we are bound; and wo be to us if we preach not the Goſpel, how can thoſe that believe, doe but ſpeak, how can thoſe that have heard and ſeen and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114525:17"/> the word and Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.1. <hi>to</hi> 3.</note> but muſt ſay with the Apoſtle how can we but ſpeake and declare thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly glorious excellent things which we have both ſeen heard and received.</p>
            <p>Therefore Reader if God ſhall perſwade thy heart to the acknowledgement of this truth, fear not to practiſe it, though men and divils ſet themſelves againſt thee,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</note> yet know that God is faithfull that promiſeth and will ſuffer no temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to overtake thee but what he will enable thee to bear: and though thou mayeſt by men be oppoſed and brought into great afflictions and tribulations,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22.</note> it is written that through ſuch we muſt enter into the kingdome of heaven,</p>
            <p>It is the Legacy that Chriſt hath left to his people, that all that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus and follow him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.</note> muſt take up his Croſſe and ſuffer perſecution, yet know he will never leave us nor forſake us, but ſtand by us, and his ſpirit of glory ſhall reſt upon us for our ſtrength-making, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about all the threſts and terrours of impriſonments,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, penalties that ſhall be layd upon us for his ſake, turne to our good and benefit; Therefore gird up the Loynes of your mindes, be ſober and hope to the end,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13.</note> for the grace that is to be brought to you at the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, feare not, neither be diſmayed,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23. <hi>and</hi> 16.13. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6.10.11.16.</note> you are bought with a price, be not the Servants of men, watch, ſtand faſt in the Faith, quit you like men, be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> on, the whole Armour of God; above all taking the Sheil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of faith whereby ye ſhall be able to ſtand againſt the wiles of the Divell, and quench all the fiery darts of the wicked;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1 12.</note> wherefore all my prayer allwayes ſhall be, that our God will count you worthy of this calling, and fulfill all the good pleaſure of his goodneſſe, and the worke of faith with power, that the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt may be glorified in you, and ye in him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the grace of God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.11.12.</note> to comfort your hearts, and ſtabliſh you in every good word, and worke. Amen,</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:114525:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pſalme</hi> 68. and 11. The Lord gave the word, great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the company of thoſe that preached it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iob.</hi> 32. and 7. to 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſaid dayes ſhall ſpeake, and mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of yeares ſhall teach wiſdome. But there is a ſpirit in man and the inſpiration of the Almighty giveth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, great men are not alwayes wiſe, neither do the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged underſtand Judgement. Therefore I ſaid heathen to me, I alſo will ſhew mine opinion.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
